"Using Prebiotics to Boost GLP-1"
Plant-predominant diets may play
a "major role in reversing
the obesity
and chronic disease epidemics,"
just as plant-based
dietary interventions
may arrest or even reverse
type 2 diabetes
and cardiovascular disease
on an individual basis.
In a previous video,
I showed how a tofu burger
boosted levels
of the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1
higher than a meat burger
in both people with diabetes
and without,
even though the two burgers
were matched
for calories
and macronutrients.
One thing may have given
the plant-based meal an edge,
though, at least over time:
increased fiber.
The bacterial fermentation
of dietary fibers in the colon
produces short-chain fatty acids
called acetate, propionate,
and butyrate, which, in turn,
stimulate release of GLP-1.
In this way, prebiotics,
like dietary fiber,
represent
an alternative strategy
for boosting production
of GLP-1.
In contrast, a bacterial
breakdown product of tryptophan,
which is concentrated
in animal protein,
has been found
to have opposite effects
on GLP-1 release.
How do we know fiber-derived
short-chain fatty acids
boost GLP-1 in the first place?
Well, all three circulating
short-chain fatty acids
were associated with
higher GLP-1 concentrations
in the blood,
but that doesn’t prove
cause-and-effect.
For that, you need to stick
tubes in people’s butts.
Getting a rectal infusion
of acetate
indeed causes GLP-1 levels
to go up.
And the amount of acetate
concentrations in the blood
reached after rectal infusion
were within an achievable range,
in the ballpark
of what you’d get
eating 15 or more grams
of fiber a day,
here in the form
of oat bran cereal and muffins.
There’s a third way
to get appetite-suppressing
short-chain fatty acids
in our bloodstream
besides the top-down approach
of eating healthy food
and the bottoms-up approach
of getting them squirted
in your tush.
When you consume vinegar,
its acetic acid is rapidly
neutralized into acetate.
Here’s the spike in acetate
in your bloodstream
that you get from consuming
about a tablespoon of vinegar
mixed in water.
No wonder vinegar
has evidently been used
to treat obesity for centuries.
Does this all translate
into reducing cravings,
eating less,
and losing weight?
Let’s scan people’s brains
and find out.
Researchers delivered
propionate,
a fiber-derived,
short-chain fatty acid,
into the colons
of study participants
while showing them images of
pizza, cakes, and chocolates,
and found that increasing
colonic propionate
seemed to reduce
brain activation
in the reward centers
of the brain.
This was accompanied by
a decrease in subjective appeal
of these kinds of foods,
they didn’t look as tasty,
and this translated
into reduced caloric intake
at a buffet meal.
Note that this effect
didn’t seem to correlate
with GLP-1 changes, though;
so, it’s possible
that short-chain fatty acids
produced in the colon
are accessing the brain directly
and reducing appetite
some other way.
Regardless,
does the boost in GLP-1
and the short-term reduction
of caloric intake
from the direct delivery
of propionate to the colon
translate into
better weight control
in overweight adults?
Yes, long-term colonic
propionate delivery
prevents body weight gain,
particularly deep abdominal fat,
and may even reduce liver fat
in those with
fatty liver disease.
So, you’d expect prebiotic
trials to show the same,
and sometimes they worked,
boosting GLP-1
and driving down hunger,
but overall, human interventions
with prebiotics
have shown mixed results.
And that’s putting it lightly.
Effects on GLP-1 appear
to be highly contradictory,
with different isolated dietary
fibers bumping GLP-1 up,
some dropping it down,
and others having no effect.
In some cases, it’s possible
that macronutrients
that would otherwise
stimulate GLP-1
might get caught up
in viscous, fibrous masses
and result in lower levels.
Regardless, results for
short-term prebiotic trials
are said to be
"completely inconclusive"
for GLP-1.
One problem may be the dose.
For example, in this study,
researchers tested
refined-grain bread
versus whole-grain bread,
and although the whole-grain
bread improved satiety,
it had no effect on GLP-1.
The difference in fiber content
was only about five grams,
though, which may not be enough.
In this study,
study participants
were randomized
to get either 5 or 10 grams
of a fiber supplement
called Fibersol,
and the five-gram dose appeared
to have no greater effect
on GLP-1 than placebo.
Only the 10-gram dose worked,
which is about two tablespoons.
Similarly, there were
significant delays in hunger
and increased satiety
after 10 grams, but not five.
And studies like this
may only last a few hours.
The more fiber-rich foods
you eat,
the more you foster the growth
of more fiber-feeders,
which means even more
GLP-1 secretion over time.
Eating more fiber-rich foods
may eventually even promote
the emergence of more
GLP-1 secreting cells
in our intestinal lining.
Check out this study.
Adaptation
of colonic fermentation
and GLP-1 secretion with
increased wheat fiber intake
for not a few hours
but an entire year.
People who eat whole grains
tend to get less diabetes,
but even if you switch to
whole wheat for weeks or months,
there doesn’t seem
to be much improvement
in blood sugar control.
It turns out
it may take longer than that
for our colon to adapt
to the increased fiber intake.
Colonic adaptation
to increased wheat fiber intake
takes many months
but eventually results
in increased
short fatty acid production
and GLP-1 secretion.
This was found
when people were randomized
to a year of either All Bran
or Rice Krispies cereal
for breakfast.
And there was
a significant increase
in short-chain
fatty acid production
and GLP-1 secretion
in the higher-fiber group,
but it took 9 to 12 months
for these benefits to develop.
And finally,
people may not understand
the complexity of dietary fiber,
thinking that
it’s a single nutrient,
but there are literally
thousands of types of fiber
in plant foods,
and each one may support
different communities
of bacteria in our gut.
That’s the reasoning
behind recommendations
that people take
a "50-food challenge,"
eating at least 50
different plant foods a week
to achieve a diet
diverse enough
to feed a vast spectrum
of bacteria.
Those who get more fiber
in their diet
are significantly less likely
to get heart disease,
and die from heart disease.
Less likely to get
cardiovascular disease
in general, and less likely
to die from it.
Less likely to have a stroke,
less likely to get diabetes
and colorectal cancer,
less likely to die
from cancer across the board,
and less likely to die
from all causes put together.
But all of this
is for fiber from food.
In terms of fiber intake
for optimal health,
the first line of defense
for disease prevention
is to focus on fiber from foods
rather than supplements.
For the treatment of disease,
there is a lack
of evidence-based research
to support the use
of most isolated fiber types.
Take that supplement Fibersol,
for example.
Fibersol is
a registered trademark
of the Matsutani
Chemical Industry Company,
the one who invented it.
"Looking to increase
the fiber content
of a finished product?
Check out
our innovation success stories."
Eat your donut cookie
whipped cream milkshake,
it’s got fiber!
Maybe better to stick to foods
that were invented instead
by Mother Nature.